Guide to the Herbert E. Huncke Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Herbert E. Huncke Papers
1946-1973.
Huncke, Herbert.
2 linear ft. (3 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0635
4078923
Writer, counter-culture figure and associate of Beat Generation writers such as Allen Ginsberg, Peter Orlovksy, and Jack Kerouac.
History
Herbert Huncke was born in Greenfield, Massachusetts in 1915, but moved as a young boy to Detroit and then Chicago where his father owned H.S. Huncke, a company that distributed machine parts.
Though Huncke grew up in a comfortable middle class household (a history he recounts in some of his pieces of writing, most notably "Love" and "Song of the Self"), his family life was not particularly smooth and he often ran away from home. When he was 17 he went to New York for the first time and, after a few years drifting around the country working odd jobs, he relocated to the city more-or-less permanently in 1939.
Over the next several years, Huncke, a junkie, drug-dealer, hustler, and small time thief, became deeply involved in the street scene that had emerged around Times Square. Though he left New York for a time during World War II to serve as a merchant marine, his return to the city meant a return to drugs and the demimonde of 42nd Street. It was as a bisexual Times Square hustler that Huncke drew Alfred Kinsey's interest and in his capacity as petty thief and mover of stolen goods that Huncke first became affiliated with the William S. Burroughs. In 1945 Burroughs approached Huncke's roommate about selling a shotgun and a cache of morphine syrettes. Though initially Huncke was deeply suspicious of the clean-cut Burroughs, the two became close friends and Huncke was adopted into Burroughs's group of young friends, including Jack Kerouac and Allen Ginsberg.
Huncke, with his history of prostitution, drug-use, and other criminal activity became a sort of talisman of authenticity for the young writers. They adopted his hipster street lingo--Huncke reputedly coined the term "beat," and his drug-fueled lifestyle and used him as an urban hipster muse (Huncke appears as a character in many of Kerouac's works, as well as Burroughs's Junky, and is mentioned in Ginsberg's "Howl.").
In the 1940s Huncke began to write more seriously himself, composing many of the stories and journal entries that he would later publish. In 1947 he briefly moved to the Texas farm where Burroughs and his wife Jean Vollmer were growing marijuana. He returned to New York where, in 1949, he was arrested for theft and did a stint in Sing Sing. He was released in 1954, but ran afoul of the law again the next year and landed back in prison, where he remained until 1959.
Upon his return to New York he reconnected with his beat friends, living for a time in the same building as Allen Ginsberg and Peter Orlovsky (with whom Huncke had a brief affair). He moved around New York's Lower East Side for most of the rest of his life. He met Louis Cartwright in the 1970s and Cartwright became Huncke's lover and primary caretaker for most of the remainder of Huncke's life. Huncke enrolled in a methadone program in an attempt to kick his heroin habit, but the program was never fully successful.
Though he began his writing in the 1940s, he found it very difficult to write in prison, so did very little writing during the 1950s. He gained some popularity giving live reading in New York City, but was not published until 1965 when Diane DiPrima's Poets Press published excerpts from his journal. His story "Alvarez" was published in Playboy in 1968 and he had small editions of his work released through small presses with Elsie John and Joey Martinez released in 1979 and The Evening Sun Turned Crimson in 1980. His autobiography Guilty of Everything: The Autobiography of Herbert Huncke was released in 1990 and a posthumous collection of his work, The Herbert Huncke Reader was published in 1997.
Herbert Huncke died in 1996 at the age of 81.
Scope and Content
This collection contains correspondence, journal entries, manuscript writings, and miscellaneous notes.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in II series:
I. Correspondence, 1946-1973
II. Writings, 1948-1971
Subjects
Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997.; Huncke, Herbert.; Orlovsky, Peter, 1933-; Nepal--Description and travel.; Beat generation.; Drugs.; Narcotics.; Drug abuse.; Prisoners.; Poets, American--20th century.; Diaries.; Authors.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
M-59 Purchase
- Series I: Correspondence, 1946-1973
  Series I consists of correspondence sent to and written by Herbert Huncke. The correspondence, much composed while Huncke was in jail, documents his varied relationships with his friends and cohorts, as well as shedding some insight onto his writings.
  The correspondence is arranged alphabetically by composer of the item, and chronologically within each writer.
  - Ginsberg, Allen to Herbert Huncke
    - 1966 September-December, (15 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1 to 15)
    - 1968 March-June, (4 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 16 to 19)
    - 1974 July- August, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 21 to 22)
  - Ginsberg, A to Louis Cartwright, 1970 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Huncke, Herbert
    - to Peter Orlovsky, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - to Louis Cartwright, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - to Allen Ginsberg
      - Circa 1946, (5 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 23 to 27)
        (with carbons)
      - 1947 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 29)
        (with handwritten manuscript)
    - to Peter Orlovsky
      - Circa 1960, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 30 to 31)
    - to Allen Gisnberg and Peter Orlovsky, 1960 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - to Eila Kokkinen, 1961 June- December (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - to Elise Cowen, 1960 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - to Howard Schuklman, 1961 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - to Howard Schulman and Elizabeth Sutherland, 1961 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - to Janine Pommey, 1962 June- August, (4 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 37 to 40)
    - To Eila Kokkinen, 1962 March- July (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - To Eila Kokkinen, 1964 February-June, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 42 to 43)
    - To Noah Goldenberg, 1964 February – April, (4 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 44 to 47)
    - To Eila Kokkinen, 1966 October 13 and December 2 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - To Gary, 1968 August 3 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - To The Ministry of Foreign Affairs [of Nepal], 1971 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - To Linda, 1971 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - To Eila Kokkinen, 1971 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - To Louis Cartwright, 1973 April-July, (3 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 53 to 55)
  - Orlovsky, Peter to Herbert Huncke, [1960] (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Pommy, Janine to Herbert Huncke, 1970 March 24 and Undated (8 letters) (Box 1, Folder 57 to 64)
- Series II: Writings, 1948-1971
  Series II is comprised of Herbert Huncke's writings, including manuscripts, notebooks, and journals. Many of the notebooks include both fragments of published and unpublished manuscripts as well as general notes and daily observations.
  - 1948
    - "Philosophizing" (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Song of the Self" (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "A Story- New York" (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - [Thoughts About Writing] (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - [The Urge to Write] (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Untitled Manuscripts, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 6 to 7)
      (includes "Alone," "Suicide," and "A Fix")
  - 1949
    - "Dear Dad Letter" (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1959
    - Criticism of a Poem (II) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Cuba" (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Dancing in Prison" (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Good Talker" (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Love" (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "A New Orleans Scene" (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "Poem" (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "Spencer’s Pad" (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "Miscellaneous and Untitled Manuscripts" (Box 2, Folder 17)
      (including "Arrested" and "Youth")
  - 1959-1960
    - Notebook and Diary Excerpts (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 1960
    - "Ed Leary" (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "A Sea Voyage-- and Junk" (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "Strangers" (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Untitled Manuscripts (Box 2, Folder 22)
      (small notebook)
  - 1961
    - Huncke's Journal, (3 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 23 to 25)
    - Notebook (Box 2, Folder 26)
      (includes draft of "The Magician")
    - Notes en Route to Lexington, July 10, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Untitled Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - 1962
    - "The Party" (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - 1963
    - Notebooks, (3 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 30 to 32)
  - 1963
    - Notebooks, (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1 to 2)
      (contains drafts of "Beware of Fallen Angels")
    - Notebooks, 1963-1966, (3 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 3 to 5)
  - 1964
    - Notebooks, (7 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 6 to 12)
      (include drafts of "In the Park" and "Russian Blackie")
    - "Ponderosa Pines (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - "Untitled Manuscript" (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - 1965
    - Notebooks, (3 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1 to 3)
      (includes draft of "Cat and his Girl")
  - 1971
    - Notebooks (Box 4, Folder 4)
      (these document Huncke's trip to Nepal)
  - Undated
    - "Alvarez" (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "A Beginning of a Portrait" (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "Detroit Redhead" (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "Faery Tale" (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - "Funny Notes" (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - "Johnie I" (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - "Johnie II" (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Journal-- typescript excerpts (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Notebooks, (4 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 13 to 16)
      (includes drafts of "New York Notes")
    - Notes (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous and Untitled Manuscripts, (5 Folders) (Folder 18 to 21)